A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of the Secretary and General Counsel, Grant Records, Organizational Grants FA1510
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of the Secretary and General Counsel, Grant Records, Organizational Grants
1973-1986
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1510
2.5 Cubic Feet 7 boxes (6 letter document containers and 1 half-letter document container)
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of Recommended Grant Action documents (RGAs) for a small subset of Ford Foundation grants from the 1970s and 1980s. These documents describe the grant amount, the start and end date of a grant, a general description, the source of funds, other grantees included, the division/office in charge of the grant, and the responsible program officer. Some files only have one RGA while others might have many (depending on grant renewals, supplementary funding, or grants for different activities). Some files also include affirmative action statements regarding a grantee's board of directors or employees.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically as it was received from the Ford Foundation.
There is one series: Recommended Grant Action Forms and Affirmative Action Statements
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary. This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:011.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research.
Ford Foundation; Grant making; Grant recipients
- Recommended Grant Action Forms and Affirmative Action Statements, 1
  - A Better Chance, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A Contemporary Theatre, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Action for Children's Television, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Supplemental support of a project designed to ensure public participation in the process of improving children's television; operating costs
  - Action for Welfare and Awakening in a Rural Environment (AWARE), 1983 July (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Support for legal services in India
  - ActionAid-Kenya Ltd., 1984 August (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Support for a project to revitalize ten village polytechnics in Kenya
  - Actors Theatre of Louisville, Inc., 1976 August (Box 1, Folder 6)
    To improve and stabilize the financial position of the Actors Theatre of Louisville
  - Addis Ababa University, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    1986 - Support for university's museum to collect and display ethnographic materials
    1984 - Support for local skills training and advanced degree training for female university staff
    1982 - Support for local skills training and advanced degree training for female university staff
    1982 - Support for academic linkages with Western and other African universities
  - Administrative Staff College of India, Hyderabad, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1986 - Support for research on farmer participation in irrigation management in India
    1980 - Training, research, and consulting services in management, Supplement No. 2
  - Adult Literacy Organization of Zimbabwe, 1984 August (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1984 - Strengthening literacy-related small enterprise training for rural women
  - Advice and Development for Migration Zones (Mexico), 1984 May (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Develop and consolidate locally-managed small-scale irrigation projects in the home communities of migrant agricultural laborers
  - Advisory Services for Better Housing Inc., 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    1979 - Support of demonstration effort to improve the operations of distressed HUD multifamily housing developments
    1978 - Supplementary partial support for a New York-based program to analyze and treat distressed multifamily housing developments
    1974 - Partial support for a New York demonstration program to analyze and treat distressed HUD-insured multifamily developments
  - Advocap, Inc., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    1. To provide support for planning supported work demonstration projects
    2. To proved increased support for research design and documentation of national supported work program
  - Advocates for Children of New York, Inc., 1980 December (Box 1, Folder 13)
    A series of four grants to three citizen education agencies to support collective and individual efforts to improve their development and management practices so as to optimize their capacities to assist with the improvement of New York City public schools
  - Affiliate Artists, Inc. (WJH), 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    1981 - Support for expansion of the Community Arts Residency Training (CART) program
    1978 - Partial support of Regional Development Demonstration Program for Administrators and Performing Artists
  - Affiliated Tribes of Northwest Indians, 1985 September (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Support for the development of tribal and intertribal archives in the Northwest
  - Africa Inland Mission, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Community relations and training programs; Hurri Hills nomadic pastoralist project, Kenya
  - Africa News Service, Inc., 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    1986 - Partial support for a program of enhanced outreach and coverage of African affairs
    1983 - Partial support to initiate a nationwide program of daily radio broadcasts on African and African issues
  - The African-American Institute, 1974-1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    1985 - (1) Conferences on African and American leaders (2) Newsletter for Southern African refugees and students in the United States
    1982 - Conferences on African and American leaders and visits of Angolan and Mozambicans to the US
    1980 - Conferences of African and American leaders
    1975 - Conferences of African and American leaders
    1974 - General support
  - African Institute for Economic Development and Planning (IDEP), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Support for a regional conference on the planning and management of shared river basins in West Africa
  - Africare, 1984 May (Box 1, Folder 20)
    US public education programs on African development
  - Afro-American Total Theatre Arts Foundation, Inc., 1979 April (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Partial support for Black Theatre Festival USA
  - Aga Khan Foundation/Kenya, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    1986 - Support for experimental community-based maternal and child health projects in Eastern Africa
    1984 - Support for experimental community-based maternal and child health projects in Kenya
  - Aga Khan Foundation/USA, 1983 April-May (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Support for the Programme's development activities in northern Pakistan
  - Agency for Instructional Television, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Matching contribution to a revolving development fund for new school television programming
  - Agro-Economic Survey Research Foundation (Indonesia), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Support for a study of rural labor markets in Java, Indonesia
  - Agudath Israel of America, Inc., 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    1979 - Continued support for the development of an independent, multi-ethnic neighborhood conservation effort in Boro Park, Brooklyn (770-0555)
    1978 - Continued support for the development of an independent, multi-ethnic neighborhood conservation effort in Boro Park, Brooklyn
    1977 - Continued support for the development of an independent, multi-ethnic neighborhood conservation effort in Boro Park, Brooklyn
  - The Agricultural Development Council, Inc., 1974-1984 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    1984 August - enhancing training and research capacities in the rural social sciences in Africa
    1984 February - Support for research, training, and professional development in the rural social sciences in Bangladesh, Supplement No. 1
    1983 - Activities relating to research and training in agricultural economics in the People's Republic of China, Supplement No. 1
    1982 June - Activities relating to research and training in agricultural economics in the People's Republic of China
    1982 April - Support to strenghten the rural social sciences in Asia
    1982 January - Bangladesh program of research, training and professional development activities in rural, social sciences
    A Report to the Ford Foundation from The Agricultural Development Council
    1980 March - Program activities in the economics of agriculture in Pakistan, Supplement No. 1
    1980 October - General support for programs to strengthen the rural social sciences in Asia, Supplement No. 3
    1977 January - Support to Indonesia's Agro-Economic Survey for a Rural Dynamics Study, Supplement No. 1
    1975 June - Support to Indonesia's Agro-Economic Survey for a Rural Dynamics Study
    1974 December - Support program of research, training and professional development activities in rural social sciences
    1974 September - Core operations support for programs to strengthen Asian rural social sciences, Supplement No. 1
    1974 August - Support to Indonesia's Agro-Economic Survey, Supplement No. 1
    1974 August - Rural social science training in Indonesia, Supplement No. 1
  - The Agricultural University of Wageningen, the Netherlands, 1986 June (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Support for research on farmer organization and the management of irrigation systems in Mexico
  - Ahfad University College for Women, Sudan, 1984 April (Box 1, Folder 29)
    To strengthen the rural extension program of the Ahfad University College for Women, Sudan
  - Ahmadu Bello University (Zaria, Nigeria), 1985 March (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Support for staff development and research on socioeconomic and management aspects of irrigation and river basin development in Nigeria
  - Ahmedabad Municipal Corporation, 1984 September (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Support for conservation studies in Jaipur and Ahmedabad cities, respectively
  - Akademi Seni Tari Indonesia, Denpasar, 1984 June (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Support for teaching and research in ethnomusicology in Indonesia
  - Alabama Center for Higher Education, Inc., 1979 July (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Help public black colleges strengthen their plans for participating in the desegregation of higher education in the South
  - Alaska Native Foundation, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    1976 - Support for a study of the twelve regional corporations charged with implementing the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act of 1971
    1975 - Continued partial support to the Alaskan Native technical assistance institution
  - Albany Medical College, 1976 August (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Research and training in reproductive science and contraceptive development
  - All Indian Pueblo Council (New Mexico), 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Support for the development of a Pueblo archives and research center
  - Allegheny Conference on Community Development, 1985 July (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Alliance to Save Energy, 1977 June (Box 1, Folder 38)
    General support for the Alliance's first year of operation
  - All-India Institute of Medical Sciences, 1985 July (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Support for training and research in community epidemiology in India
  - Alternate Roots, Inc., 1981 December (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Administrative support of service organization for Southern community-based theaters
  - Alternative Schools Network, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Alverno College, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Support of three urban oriented higher education projects to improve educational services to minority and disadvantaged students
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1976-1985 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    1985 September - partial support for a study of decision support systems for managing large international river basins
    1985 July - support for two special issues of Daedalus: one on Indian and one on Eastern Europe; and support to test the feasibility of an issue on Western Europe
    1983 May - partial support for the European Security Study
    1983 February - partial support for United States participation, through the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, in the International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis (IISA)
    1980 June - Supplemental support for publication of an edition of Daedalus dealing with racial matters
    1978 February - Partial support for preparation of a special edition of Daedalus on Africa
    1976 May - Support for American Academy/National Academy Joint Committee on UNESCO
    1977 October - Supplemental support for publication of an edition of Daedalus dealing with racial matters
    1980 February - Partial support for a special issue of Daedalus on "US Defense Polucy in the 1980s"
    1977 April - Partial support for a special issue of Daedalus on "The New Europe Revisited"
  - American Arbitration Association, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    1979 September - support for a project using third party techniques to resolve disputes in the academic community
    1978 July - support of Sloan Commission on Government and Higher Education project on the use of third-party techniques to disputes in the higher education field
    1978 June - continues support of Community Dispute Services for applying theird-party techniques to disputes
    1974 June - continues support for the National Center for Dispute Settlement for applying third party techniques to disputes
    1976 October - continues support of Community Dispute Services for applying theird-party techniques to disputes
    Affirmative Action Plan of the American Arbitration Association
  - American Association for the Advancement of the Humanities WJH, 1978 June (Box 1, Folder 45)
    partial support for membership development and related activities
  - American Association for Higher Education, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    1981 - publish policy research papers and conduct policy seminars for journalists
    1976 - partial support of NEXUS, and information linking service to higher education
  - American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, 1984 September (Box 1, Folder 47)
    partial for three studies related to the preparation and development of teachers
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1974-1984 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    1984 - Support for the AAAS Clearinghouse on Science and Human Rights in its efforts to prevent human rights violations and to involve scientists in the US and selected Third World Countries in human rights concerns
    1983 - Support for projects to improve mathematics education for minority students
    1974 - support for two projects to provide graduate interns and post graduate fellows for the Office of Technology Assessment
  - American Association for the Advancement of Slavik Studies, 1975-1984 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    1984 September - Matching grant for endowment fund
    1980 August - support for research development activities in Soviet studies, Supplement No. 3
    1979 February - support for research development activities in Soviet Studies, Supplement No. 2
    1977 December - support for research development activities in Soviet studies, Supplement No. 1
    1975 November - support for research development activities in Soviet studies
  - American Association of Community and Junior Colleges, 1978 March (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Support to strengthen the Association's international education program
  - American Association of State Colleges and Universities, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    1981 - partial support of a senior consultancy strategic planning service
    1979 - partial support of annual reports of higher education institutional financial indicators
    1978 - support for two-year national information gathering and dissemination project re urban-oriented higher education institutions and programs
  - American Association of University Professors, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    support of five policy oriented research and data collection projects on the academic labor market
  - American Bar Association Fund for Public Education, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    1979 - support for a program to reduce court delays and the cost of litigation
    1976 - continued support for the Commission on Correctional Facilities and Services of the American Bar Association
    1975 - to provide a national vehicle for the exchange of information on significant projects in correctional reform
    1974 - continued support for the Commission on Correctional Facilities and Services of the American Bar Association
    1974 - to provide support for a program and film in connection with the American Bar Association Annual Meeting
    1974 - support of a two-year study of the legal requirements affecting the implementation of law-related education programs in American elementary and secondary schools
    1974 - to provide an exchange of information nationally on significant projects in correctional reform
  - American Civil Liberties Union Foundation, 1976-1986 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    1986 - Support for the ACLU Foundation's work on behalf of women
    1984 - Support for litigation, advocacy and technical assistance work in the areas of voting, employment, capital punishment and attorneys' fees
    1984 - Support for the ACLU Foundation's work on behalf of women
    1983 - Support to establish a National Fund for Alien and Immigration Rights
    1982 - Continued support for women's law center for its litigation, technical assistance and educational activities
    1980 - Continued support for women's law center for its litigation, technical assistance and educational activities
    1978 - Continued support for program of prison reform advocacy
    1978 - Continued support for women's law center for its litigation, technical assistance and educational activities
    1976 - Partial support for Women's Rights Project to expand its litigation program and to increase its technical assistance and educational activities
  - American Composers Orchestra, New York, New York, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    support for marketing/audience development
  - American Council for Emigres in the Professions, Inc., 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    1977 - program to facilitate placement in the United States of scholars and intellectuals recently emigrated from the Soviet Union, Supplement No. 3
    1977 - program to facilitate placement in the United States of scholars and intellectuals recently emigrated from the Soviet Union, Supplement No. 2
    1975 - program to facilitate placement in the United States of scholars and intellectuals recently emigrated from the Soviet Union, Supplement No. 1
    1974 - program to facilitate placement in the United States of scholars and intellectuals recently emigrated from the Soviet Union
  - American Council for Nationalities Service (Washington, D.C.), 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    1986 - General support for public education and policy analyses about refugee issues
    1984 - Support to raise the level of public awareness of refugee issues and to provide analysis and reporting for policymakers and practitioners
    1983 - Support to raise the level of public awareness of refugee issues and to provide analysis and reporting for policymakers and practitioners
  - American Council of Learned Societies Devoted to Humanistic Studies, 1974-1982 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    1982 September - Partial support of core program
    1982 August - Support of the activities of the International Research and Exchange Board
    1982 April - Program of fellowships and scholarships in American studies for scholard from abroad
    1981 June - Support for research awards and research planning
    1981 May - Program of fellowships and scholarships in American studies for scholars from abroad, Supplement No. 3
    1980 August - Support for program of fellowships and scholarships in American studies for scholars from abroad, Supplement No. 2
    1980 August - Support of studies of Chinese civilization (Supplement No. 2)
    1979 May - Support for program of fellowships and scholarships in American studies for scholars from abroad, Supplement No. 1
    1978 September - Support for ACLS/SSRC joint programs in Slavic and East European Studies, Supplement No. 6
    1978 July - Support for International Research and Exchanges Board (IREX) programs of exchange, fellowships and projects involving the US, USSR, and Eastern Europe, Supplement #3
    1977 December - (1) Support for research development activities in Soviet Studies, Supplement No. 1, (2) Support for ACLS/SSRC joint programs in Slavic and East European Studies, Supplement No. 5
    1976 September - Support of studies of Chinese civilization; Support of the American Council on Learned Societies Devoted to Humanistic Studies' scholarly activities in East Asian studies, Supplement No. 2
    1976 June - Support for International Research and Exchanges Board (IREX) programs of exchange, fellowships and projects involving the US, USSR, and Eastern Europe, Supplement No. 2
    1975 November - Support for ACLS/SSRC joint programs in Slavic and East European Studies, Supplement No. 4
    1975 July - Support of study on problems of East Asian libraries
    1975 January - Exchange program with Poland, administered by International Research and Exchanges Board
    1974 July - Support for International Research and Exchanges Board (IREX) programs of exchange, fellowships and projects involving the US, USSR, and Eastern Europe, Supplement No. 1
    1975 June - National Endowment for the Humanities (Grantee) - Partial support of a National Enquiry into the Production and Dissemination of Scholarly Knowledge
    1975 May - Terminal support for program of fellowships and scholarships in American studies for scholars from abroad
    1974 July - Postdoctoral fellowships for South Asian studies, Supplement No. 2
  - American Council of Voluntary Agencies for Foreign Service, Inc., 1982 November (Box 2, Folder 59)
    Support to facilitate the effective design and implementation of rehabilitation projects for refugees in Somalia
  - American Council on Education, 1974-1985 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    1985 - Partial support of an Office of Minority Concerns working with all U.S. higher education
    1983 - Support for study of the effects of state oversight of the affairs of state univerisities
    1981 - Partial support of an Office of Minority Concerns working with all U.S. higher education
    1980 - Partial support of the National Student Aid Coalition
    1980 - Support for the establishmen of a Division of International Educational Relations
    1981 - To review and assess the status of the desegregation of public higher education and assist selected black public institutions engaged in the process
    1978 - Support of post-Bakke meetings for high-demand academic programs